Guide to the Bobbye S. Ortiz Papers, 1919-1993 and undated (bulk 1950-1990) RL.00978
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bobbye S. Ortiz papers
1919-1993 and undated, bulk 1950-1990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ortiz, Bobbye S.
RL.00978
30.4 Linear Feet
Bobbye Ortiz was a social activist and Marxist feminist. The collection consists chiefly of personal correspondence; extensive subject files on international political and cultural movements; photographs and slides; ephemeral publication material such as grassroots newsletters, pamphlets, broadsides, and clippings; cultural artifacts, including buttons and T-shirts; and over 300 sound recordings of spoken voice and music (see separate catalog record for sound recordings). The collection documents the personal life and career of an international feminist, Marxist activist, and mother, who also served as editor of the magazine Monthly Review and was the founder of the organization WIRE (Women's International Resource Exchange). English.
12,430 Items
Access Restrictions
Parts of the collection are closed to research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
In addition, some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible because they require further processing before use (see the finding aid for details).
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rubenstein Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Bobbye S. Ortiz were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts from her daughter Victoria Ortiz in 1992, 1994, and 2003.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1918, July 2 Born in Memphis, Tenn.
1928-1929 Attended Lockhart-Moore Academy, Little Rock, Ark.
1929-1930 Attended Fassifern School, Hendersonville, N.C.
1930-1932 Attended Kidd-Key College and Conservatory, Sherman, Tex.
1932-1933 Henderson State Teachers College, Arkadelphia, Ark.
1933-1935 Undergraduate at Barnard College at age 15
1935-1937 University of Chicago
1939-1944 Lived in Mexico
1939 Married to Robert G. Colodny, separated 1940
1940-1952 Married to Cesar Ortiz
1942, May 6 Daughter Victoria born
1951-1953 Studied at the Sorbonne, Paris and traveled extensively in Europe
1953-1956 Lived in England
1957 Returned to United States
1960 B.A. in Spanish, New York University
1963 M.A. in Spanish, New York University
1963, Fall Teaching assistant in Spanish, NYU
1968-1983 Associate Editor, Monthly Review
1979 Co-founder of WIRE (Women's International Resource Exchange)
1989 Awarded the Arthur J. Felberbaum Award from the New York Marxist School
1990, June 15 Died, New York City
Collection Overview
The papers of feminist and social activist Bobbye Ortiz span from the years 1919 to 1993, with most of the papers being dated between 1950 and 1990. The papers consist chiefly of personal correspondence; extensive subject files on international political and cultural movements; photographs and slides; ephemeral publication material such as grassroots newsletters, pamphlets, broadsides, and clippings; cultural artifacts, including buttons and T-shirts; and over 300 sound recordings of spoken voice and music. The collection documents the personal life and career of an international feminist, Marxist activist, and mother, who also served as editor of the magazine Monthly Review and was the founder of the organization WIRE (Women's International Resource Exchange). Other personal documents and subject files concern the activities of Bobbye's daughter, Viki Ortiz, an activist in her own right. The materials in both women's files are especially rich in the history of the international women's liberation movement and other revolutionary movements in Europe, Latin America, and other countries during the sixties, seventies, and eighties. Many of these materials focus on politics and government in Cuba, China, and France. Other topics include Vietnam War protests; students' movements, particularly Paris, 1968; indigenous women's movements in Latin America; AIDS activism; sexual health; adoption rights; gay and lesbian parenting; and women's issues such as reproductive rights, economic status, and violence against women.
The Correspondence Series is almost completely CLOSED to research; see the inventory below for more information. Most materials in other series, however, are open for research.
The Personal Files Series focuses on Ortiz's formal education, particularly her coursework at New York University. Other highlights of the series include Ortiz's scrapbook from her tour of China, which is further documented by audio tapes and photographs in the collection. Writings folders include notes, short articles, and speeches written by Ortiz as well as a collection of poetry by Grace Goldin, a friend of Ortiz. Two folders contain photocopies of inscriptions from many authors found inside the volumes in her personal library (now in the Perkins Library stacks of Duke University). This series is partially CLOSED.
The Subject Files Series has been separated into two main subseries: one devoted to international women's liberation and one for general topics. In the International Women's Liberation Subseries, Ortiz maintained extensive files on the status of women and women's liberation campaigns around the world. The grassroots organizational publications (many of them ephemeral in nature), news clippings, and articles found in the international women's liberation subseries address such issues as women's economic status, their roles in the family, violence against women, reproductive rights and sexuality, and indigenous women's movements. The most extensive segments of the subseries deal with women's liberation in the 1970s and 1980s in Chile, Cuba, the Dominican Republic, El Salvador, Eritrea, Guatemala, Mexico, Nicaragua, and the United States. The subseries is organized alphabetically by country.
The General Files Subseries consists mainly of articles, notes, and periodicals from the 1960s, 1970s and 1980s. Especially noteworthy are notes and other papers related to Ortiz's work as associate editor of the Monthly Review, though these provide only a limited glimpse into her decades of service there. The subseries also contains materials related to health, cancer, and the right-to-die movement; feminism, women's liberation, and the Women's International Resource Exchange (WIRE); and the political turmoil of Paris 1968. Together, Ortiz's subject files reflect the directions of her activism in the final decades of her life.
The Photographs and Slides Series contains portraits of individuals and groups, photographs taken during tours of countries and political events, and miscellaneous casual snapshots. There are very fine portraits of native peoples taken by well-known activist Gertrude Duby Blom. The largest segment of the series documents Ortiz's trips to China in 1974 and Latin America (ca. 1984). For related materials, see the Audio Tapes Series and the Personal Files Series. There are also audio cassettes recorded in Latin America and Nicaragua, which may correspond with slides in the Photographs and Slides Series. This series ends with photo negatives of an International Women's Day March in 1978. Note: This series is restricted. Use copies must be made of any cassettes without use copies already made. Please consult with reference staff.
Posters, buttons, and T-shirts bearing slogans and vivid images were vital components of the many social movements in which both Bobbye and Victoria Ortiz participated. The Cultural Artifacts Series captures the political use of popular culture in the late 20th century by preserving a representative sample of these cultural artifacts. The selections reflect Bobbye and Viki's participation in social movements concerned with issues such as U.S. imperialism in Latin America, international women's liberation, AIDS, and lesbian and gay rights. The series also contains original artwork done for Bobbye and Viki, as well as art posters from France. Several oversize posters are artifacts from the French worker/student strikes of 1968.
The majority of tapes in the Audio Tapes Series are cassette recordings of tours taken by Bobbye Ortiz during her travels in China and Latin America. Additional tapes include recordings of radio programs, interviews, and readings related to Bobbye's activism. Descriptive notes on many of the tapes listed below have been included as an appendix to this inventory. Note: This series is restricted. Use copies must be made of any cassettes without use copies already made. Please consult with reference staff. Related material about these trips may also be found in the Photographs and Slides Series and Personal Files Series.
The complete holdings of Bobbye Ortiz's library, which were donated as part of this collection and reside in Perkins Library at Duke University, are represented by the hand-written Index Card Catalog Series. The hundreds of Monthly Review Press publications in the library are one of the few records in the Ortiz Collection of her work for over twenty years as associate editor of the Monthly Review. The range of topics covered by her library -- women, Marxism and socialism, literature, Central America, Latin America, Asia, social sciences, humanities -- reveals the breadth of her intellectual interests and their intimate connections to her political concerns. The catalog is organized by topic, alphabetically by author therein.
The Phonograph Records Series features sound recordings on 33 1/3, 45, and 78 LPs collected by Bobbye Ortiz during her travels. Hundreds of folk music recordings, protest and labor song collections, and miscellaneous spoken word recordings date from the 1960s to the 1980s. Recording artists include many well-known musicians as well as hundreds of other musicians interested in folk, labor, and protest music; major languages represented include Spanish, French, and Italian. Many of these recordings are now out of print and difficult to find. This series is restricted: use copies must be made in order to access the recordings. For assistance, please contact the reference staff.
The addition (Acc.# 2003-0065) consists largely of photographs and negatives (approximately 550 prints, 120 negatives, and 1 slide, color and black-and-white), documenting Ortiz's travels to various locations including Cuba, Nicaragua, China, Mexico, the Dominican Republic, and Europe (1968-[1980s]). Also included are publication files related to WIRE (Women's International Resource Exchange), a few pieces of correspondence, and other miscellaneous personal items. Boxes 2 and 3, containing photographs, correspondence, and personal items, are CLOSED to research. Box 1 is open to research. No container list was created for this accession.
Slides (photographs); Scrapbooks; Photographs; Social activists -- Correspondence; Women's periodicals; Women -- Social conditions; Feminists -- Correspondence; Communism; Nineteen sixties; Social movements -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Radicalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements; Adoption; Civil rights movements -- Mississippi; Protest songs; Folk music; Indigenous peoples -- Portraits; Student movements -- France; Italy -- Social conditions; South America -- Social conditions; Latin America -- Social conditions -- 1948; Mexico -- Social conditions; Central America -- Social conditions; China -- Social conditions; Cuba -- History -- Revolution, 1959; Mothers and daughters; Feminism; Posters; Ortiz, Bobbye S.; Women's International Resource Exchange Service; Ortiz, Victoria, 1942-
- Correspondence Series, 1990
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Boxes 1-7 contain materials that are closed to research until 2050. Box 8 consists of materials related to Bobbye's passing away in 1990 and is open to research.
  - Condolences upon BSO's death, 1990 (4 folders) (open for research) (Box 8)
  - Guestbook for BSO wake, 1990 June 16-18 (open for research) (Box 8)
- Personal Files Series, [192-]-1989 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Chiefly documents Bobbye Ortiz's formal education. Contains Ortiz's scrapbook from a tour of China, further documented through audio tapes and photographs in other sections of the collection. Writings include pieces by Ortiz as well as poems by her close friend Grace Goldin. Book inscriptions are photocopied from holdings in Ortiz's library. Organized alphabetically by folder title.
  [This series contains materials that are CLOSED (early education folders in box 9A). See the container list below for details. Contact Research Services.]
  - Articles about BSO (Box 8)
  - Awards, 1972, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Barnard Collection (Box 8)
  - Berkshire Forum, 1984 (Box 8)
  - Brooklyn Women's Studies Talk (Box 8)
  - China Trip -- Scrapbook, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Robert Colodny -- Book Review (Box 8)
  - box 9A (Box 9A)
    [CLOSED until 2025.]
  - Education -- Sorbonne, [ca. 1952]-1953 (Box 9B)
  - Education -- NYU Transcripts and Honors, 1959-1963 (Box 9B)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Classic Civ.), 1959 (folder 1) (Box 9B)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Classic Civ.), 1959 (folder 2) (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Math, Phys.), 1959-1963 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Span. Lit.), 1960-1963 ca. (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Spanish?), 1959-1963 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Spanish 241), 1959-1963 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (El Cid), 1959-1963 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Spanish), 1959-1963 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Spanish), 1959-1963 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Spanish), 1959 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (French), 1959-1963 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (French Renaissance Poets), 1959-1960 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (French -- Pre-Romantics), 1959-1963 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (19th Century Realist Novel), 1959-1960 (Box 10)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (French), 1960 (Box 11)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Diderot), 1959-1963 (Box 11)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (French), 1961 (Box 11)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Spanish Papers), 1959-1960 (Box 11)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (Spanish Papers), ca. 1959-1963 (Box 12)
  - Education -- NYU Coursework (French Papers), 1959-1960 (Box 12)
  - Education -- Teaching Appointment at NYU/ 1963 (Box 12)
  - Official Tags (Box 12)
  - Obituaries of Bobbye Ortiz, and her father, Louis Suckle (Box 12)
  - Resum, 1962 (Box 12)
  - Speech, 1981-- Laura Allende Memorial Service (Box 12)
  - Summons -- Arrest at Central America Demonstration, U.S., 1984 (Box 12)
  - Writings -- BSO, 1981-1986 and undated (Box 12)
  - Writings -- BSO, Unidentified Notes, ca. 1970s (Box 12)
  - Writings -- Grace Goldin, Winter's Rise: Poems on Aging, [ca.1980], with letter to BSO, and BSO's comments on poems (Box 12)
  - Writings -- Book Inscriptions (2 folders) (Box 12)
- Subject Files Series, 1938-[198-] and undated (bulk, 1960-1984)
  Consists chiefly of articles, reports, newsclippings, broadsides, and many ephemeral publications such as political newsletters and pamphlets gathered by Bobbye Ortiz throughout her life. Materials particularly provide a context for political movements and agendas of the sixties, seventies, and eighties. Divided into two subseries: International Women's Liberation and General.
  - International Women's Liberation Subseries, 1938-[198-] and undated (bulk 1960-1989)
    Topics concentrate on all issues important to women's liberation movements, especially violence against women, economic justice, and women's health issues. Many of the publications are ephemeral, prime examples being the grassroots feminist newsletters produced in Latin American countries, and the broadsides and pamphlets connected with political events such as rallies or protests. After English, Spanish is the most common language used in these materials. Organized alphabetically by country.
    - Africa -- General (Box 12)
    - Albania (Box 12)
    - Algeria (Box 12)
    - Argentina (Box 12)
    - Asia -- General (Box 12)
    - Bolivia (Box 12)
    - Brazil (Box 12)
    - Brazil -- Feminist Newspapers (Box 12)
    - Canada (Box 12)
    - Caribbean (Box 12)
    - Caribbean -- "Concerning Women and Development" (articles) (Box 12)
    - Central America -- General (Box 13)
    - Chile (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Chile -- AFWIC (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Articles (clippings) (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Bulletins, Periodicals (complete) A-F (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Bulletins, Periodicals (complete) G-P (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Bulletins, Periodicals (complete) Q-Z (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Organizational Publications -- CODEM (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Organizational Publications -- CODEPU, COSECH, CHILESOCID CAMPAIGN (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Organizational Publications -- MIR, MEMCH (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Organizational Publications -- Women for Chile (Box 13)
    - Chile -- Papers, Chapters from Books (Box 14)
    - Chile -- Platforms, Handouts, Flyers, Posters, Poetry (Box 14)
    - Chile -- Women (Box 14)
    - China (Box 14)
    - Colombia (Box 14)
    - Costa Rica (Box 14)
    - Cross-Cultural Studies: A-M (Box 14)
    - Cross-Cultural Studies: N-Z (Box 14)
    - Cross-Cultural Studies -- Materials on Health Issues in Spanish (Box 14)
    - Cuba (Box 14)
    - Cuba -- 1968 (Box 15)
    - Cuba -- Articles (Box 15)
    - Cuba -- "Housing in Revolutionary Cuba" (Oversize) (Box 15)
    - Cuba -- Miscellaneous Documents (Box 15)
    - Cuba -- Papers, Book Excerpts (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Articles (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- CEDEE (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Informational Documents: Class-Related Issues (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Informational Documents: Education-Related Issues (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Informational Documents: Health-Related Issues (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Informational Documents: Women's liberation (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Informational Documents: Work-Related Issues (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Literacy Programs (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Lyrics to Songs (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Newspapers (Box 15)
    - Dominican Republic -- Pamphlets and Flyers; Press Releases; Posters (Box 16)
    - Dominican Republic -- Periodicals (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Eastern Europe (Box 16)
    - Ecuador (Box 16)
    - Egypt (Box 16)
    - El Salvador (Box 16)
    - El Salvador -- AMES Materials (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - El Salvador -- Articles (Box 16)
    - El Salvador -- BPR Materials (Box 16)
    - El Salvador -- Flyers, Pamphlets, Photos, Posters (Box 16)
    - El Salvador -- Periodicals and Bulletins (complete) (Box 16)
    - El Salvador -- Solidarity Materials (Box 16)
    - England (Box 16)
    - Eritrea -- Articles (Box 16)
    - Eritrea -- Book Excerpts (Box 16)
    - Eritrea -- National Union of Eritrean Women and Eritrean Relief Committee Materials (Box 16)
    - Eritrea -- Photographs (Box 16)
    - Ethiopia (Box 16)
    - Greece (Box 16)
    - Grenada (Box 16)
    - Guatemala -- Fuerzas Armadas Rebeldes (FAR periodical) (Box 16)
    - Guatemala -- Informador Guerrillero (periodical) (Box 16)
    - Guatemala -- Materials in English (Box 17)
    - Guatemala -- Materials in Spanish (Box 17)
    - Guatemala -- Opinion Politica (Box 17)
    - Guatemala -- Poems (Box 17)
    - Guatemala -- The Voice of the Women (periodical) (Box 17)
    - Guyana (Box 17)
    - Haiti (Box 17)
    - Honduras (Box 17)
    - India (Box 17)
    - Indonesia (Box 17)
    - Iran (Box 17)
    - Ireland (Box 17)
    - Israel (Box 17)
    - Italy (Box 17)
    - Jamaica (Box 17)
    - Japan (Box 17)
    - Kenya (Box 17)
    - Korea (Box 17)
    - Latin America, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Latin America, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Latin America -- Exiles (Box 18)
    - Latin America -- mujer/fempress (Box 18)
    - Mexico (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- "Ahi va el golpe" (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- Articles from Newspapers and Magazines (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- Calaveras resurrectas (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- CIDHAL (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- Documents: Education and Health Related Issues (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- Documents: Feminist Cooperatives and Organizations (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- Documents: Movimiento Urbano Popular (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- Documents: Work Issues (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- Mexican Art and Life, 1938 (Box 18)
    - Mexico -- Nosotras (Box 19)
    - Mexico -- Periodicals (Box 19)
    - Mexico -- "Popular" Bulletins (complete) (Box 19)
    - Mexico -- Posters, Flyers, Pamphlets (2 posters oversize) (Box 19)
    - Mexico -- Scholarly Articles (Box 19)
    - Mexico -- Teatro Mexicano de Masas, 1955 (Box 19)
    - Middle East (Box 19)
    - Morocco (Box 19)
    - Nicaragua includes cartoon book, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Nicaragua -- AMNLAE (Box 19)
    - Nicaragua -- Articles (Box 19)
    - Nicaragua -- Documents: Feminist Organizations and Law Reform Groups (Box 19)
    - Nicaragua -- Documents: Oficina de la mujer, 1984 (Box 20)
    - Nicaragua -- Liberation Theology (Box 20)
    - Nicaragua -- Newspapers (Box 20)
    - Nicaragua -- Theological Studies and the Role of Women (Box 20)
    - Pacific -- General (Box 20)
    - Pakistan (Box 20)
    - Palestine (Box 20)
    - Panama (Box 20)
    - Peru -- Articles (Box 20)
    - Peru -- Documents: Education Issues (Box 20)
    - Peru -- Information on Flora Tristan and Materials from Flora Tristan Center (Box 20)
    - Peru -- Periodicals (complete) (Box 20)
    - Philippines (Box 20)
    - Puerto Rico (Box 21)
    - Sahara (Box 21)
    - Saudi Arabia (Box 21)
    - Singapore (Box 21)
    - South Asia (Box 21)
    - Southern Africa (Box 21)
    - Soviet Union (Box 21)
    - Spain (Box 21)
    - Spain -- Periodicals (Box 21)
    - Sri Lanka (Box 21)
    - Tanzania (Box 21)
    - Thailand (Box 21)
    - Trinidad and Tobago (Box 21)
    - United States -- Articles -- Mainstream Publications (Box 21)
    - United States -- Feminism -- Academia (Box 21)
    - United States -- Feminism, Theories, Issues of Racism, Homophobia, Rape (Box 21)
    - United States -- Feminist Periodicals (Box 22)
    - United States -- "Social and Political Bases of Female Sterilization" (Box 22)
    - United States -- Women of Color and Black Women (Box 22)
    - United States -- Women's Movement Literature (Box 22)
    - Uruguay (Box 22)
    - Venezuela (Box 22)
    - Vietnam (Box 22)
    - Zimbabwe (Box 22)
  - General Files Subseries, [196-]-[198-] and undated
    Cover a number of topics, including feminism in Britain, France, and Italy; racism around the world; the right-to-die movement; liberation theology; and colonialism. Contains many periodical publications, mostly in single issues. A substantial group of materials, including ephemeral publications and memorabilia, originated from the 1968 Paris student-worker uprisings. Organized alphabetically by folder titles.
    - Against Racism: Newsletter of the Anti-Racism Literature Project (Box 22)
    - American Student Union (Box 22)
    - Berkshire Forum (Box 22)
    - Jacqui Bernard Murder -- Clips (Box 22)
    - Bias Education Materials (Box 22)
    - British Feminist Publications (Box 22)
    - Guion Julia de Burgos and Sin Venda (Box 22)
    - Cancer Articles (Box 22)
    - CIIR Publications (Box 22)
    - Citizen Soldier (Box 22)
    - Colonialism -- Encyclopedia Britannica reprints (Box 22)
    - Concern for Dying Newsletter (Box 22)
    - Cuba Petition, 1963 (Box 22)
    - Da Internacional de la Mujer Trabajadora (Box 22)